Okay, so let's start today.
We'll begin with a quick recap of last
week's class.
So we were slowly getting onto the
bandwagon or the concept of cloud.
So we first identified how do we define
cloud,
what are the common traits of a cloud
ecosystem, and then we
covered the first basic pillar of cloud,
that is the three service models.
Now we are still on the NIST's 3, 4,
5 rule.
So today hopefully we will complete the
next two sections,
which is the four and five, how you can,
the thing.
So yesterday we saw like what is the
cloud comprised of like.
What all things I can do now?
The next step or action today,
which we'll be seeing, is like,
having seen the cloud,
how can I make use of it, or like,
what is in it for me? So,
that are the things which are there.
Most of these things you would have.
Pretty much known,
so it's like I will just do a definition
brush up, and in case any questions,
we'll take it on the way. So,
the next step,
which we call as the deployment models.
are the ones which we are going to see.
So if you remember in our earlier classes,
we said like there are four deployment
models.
And anybody has any idea as to what those
deployment models are?
No, those are the service model, IAS,
PaaS,
and things are the services which you can
offer. Deployment model means, like,
how can you consume those service models?
IAS, Paas, and things, infrastructure,
software as a service, and...
What was the other platform as a service?
Are the offerings of Cloud with certain
characteristics? So,
if you want to buy hardware,
you go subscribe to an infrastructure as
a service provider.
The infrastructure platform as a service
provider is this. Now,
it is just like this thing, like you have.
Netflix, you have Hotstar,
you have Prime Video,
you have other things.
How do you want to utilize them?
Depends upon how you want to complete
other things. Netflix,
some of you would go and say, like, okay,
I'm just going to use the mobile only
version.
But whereas some of you might say, like,
okay, no, no, I have a better,
bigger TV invested. I have a lot of...
money invested in a home theater system,
so I will go for the Netflix Ultra
version.
So that is what is this deployment models
in cloud,
which we are going to talk about.
So when I talk about public cloud,
private cloud, community cloud,
hybrid cloud,
it applies to all the service models
which we are taking.
If you see our previous definitions.
So if you see infrastructures,
this models can be obtained as public or
private infrastructure or combination of
both.
This will be common across all AS models.
So like whether you take infrastructure,
whether you take platform,
or whether you take software as a service,
it doesn't matter.
Everything is going to be.
consumed under these, what do you call,
like deployment models which we have.
So if you see the diagram here,
like you have an infrastructure as a
cloud,
which can be taken as a private cloud,
which can be taken as a community cloud,
which can be taken as a public cloud,
which can be taken as a hybrid cloud.
So the objective of today's session is
going to define what a private cloud is,
what a public cloud is,
what a community cloud is,
what a hybrid cloud is.
Fair warning,
it might look confusing at the first go
because everything is like off your
premises and there might be a thin line
which separates. But again,
the way you share the resources is what
it defines these kind of labeling
attached to.
the service model consumption pattern
will be called for.
I'll explain it as we go along.
The first thing.
Right, public, private, and things. Now,
the first thing which we talk about is
public cloud. As the name suggests,
it's pretty much the thing
straightforward. When we say public cloud,
it means like the service can be deployed
by anybody who is willing to subscribe to
that particular service.
Right? It's as simple as this thing.
It's like a public transportation service.
Now,
if you want to go and then go on board a
metro,
that is a public service option available
to everybody. There is no discrimination.
There is no this thing.
As long as you pay the fare,
adhere to the rules of carriage,
you adhere to the contract of carriage
and things like that, you do.
Any public transportation,
like trains and things like that. Now,
if you consider that,
if you take the example of Indian
Railways,
the entire service is being operated by
the Indian Railways Organization.
What do they give us?
They give us the flexibility to travel on
different routes. Wherever they operate,
you can book a train and then you can go
and then do these things. Now.
I'll just jump the gun and then tell you
certain things,
which sort of resonates with the public
cloud and cloud ecosystem.
Since I've used railways,
I'll use this thing. Now, railways,
you must,
when you want to go or travel on a ticket,
what do you do?
You go onto the IRCT site and then book a
tickets. Now,
there are two types of tickets.
trains, which are regular trains,
and then there is this dynamic pricing
trains.
What is the feature of this dynamic
pricing trains?
The closer you get towards the date of
journey, the fare keeps increasing.
So that is a dynamic pricing kind of
decision. But in both the cases,
what are you doing?
You are reserving a seat.
In the sense like you are reserving a
resource to be used at a later stage.
So you're saying like, okay,
I'm going to travel,
let's say three months down the line.
Diwali is coming,
so I need to book my tickets.
So I'll book my tickets traveling from so
on and so forth. Sorry,
this is my source and this is my
destination.
And this is the class of travel I'm going
to. So it might be sleeper,
it might be third AC,
it might be second AC, first AC,
or a separate coach.
You can book or charter a separate coach
for yourself. Now,
what is the differentiating factor
between each class? The price.
If you book in a sleeper class, it's very,
very nominal price.
Then the price keeps going up as you
increase your, what do you call,
like the class of travel.
So as you upgrade yourself in the class
of travel, you pay more.
So from sleeper to 3rd AC to 2nd AC to
1st AC.
the fare keeps going up.
Now add to it the complexity of the
dynamic fare. So for example,
let's say you're booking on Rajani.
The dynamic fare also keeps increasing,
right?
So all these things are applicable in the
cloud ecosystem also.
Like when you talk about AWS, Amazon,
and all those things, these concepts.
are called as like, you know,
reserved instance and on the spot
instance.
Like the dynamic fair pricing sort of
tends to be on the spot.
Some of you who do regular workloads will
reserve some instance with Amazon and say
like, okay,
this is my daily business as usual
workload,
so I need to have these many resources
for
working. So I go and reserve it.
So for the provider like Amazon or Google
or whoever it may be,
it's easy to provision it.
But now suddenly you come and say, like,
okay, I'm cutting the queue.
I need this and things like that.
I have to go out of my way to provision
something for you.
I do manage that because I'm a cloud
provider and that is my business.
I cannot say like, okay,
only reserved people will come.
Indian Railways doesn't do that, right?
Like for people who come there out of the
thing,
what happens is like you have this satkal
key and you pay an extra satkal fee onto
this thing to get onto the train.
Similarly,
for on-the-spot instances when you want
to access.
You have to pay extra.
We will again revisit this when we talk
about the AWS and things like that,
but the concepts are same. Now,
coming back to public cloud,
public cloud is a cloud infrastructure
owned and operated by a cloud service
provider. In this case,
who is the cloud service provider?
In our example, Indian during this.
So when we talk about AWS,
AWS will build your data centers,
all the necessary security software,
hardware, procuring, compliance, blah,
blah, blah,
everything will be done by AWS team.
Now they have built huge data centers
across the world and then they keep
building and then adding every six months
to a year.
They keep adding new new centers.
So these purpose of having these data
centers is to have a global network of
Cloud infrastructure services available.
So whoever wants to join their bandwagon
can be easily serviced.
And how are these services given to you?
It is,
we are in the services consumption mode,
so there is no one-time cost.
It is always a subscription model.
So now that is where the world is heading
to, right? From a one-time purchase cost,
we have migrated into a pay-as-you-go
kind of situation.
So you use it for some time.
and you are billed for the duration at
which you use.
So, clear about public cloud.
Public cloud is nothing but the tools,
services,
and other cloud computing services.
It can be infrastructure,
it can be platform, it can be software,
offered as a this thing. Now,
example of cloud computing SaaS is like
Gmail.
You can just log on to Gmail and then get
it for you. Nothing installed.
Like you have the entire Google,
what do you call it,
workbench kind of this thing,
which includes mail, chats, et cetera,
Microsoft Teams and things like that.
So it doesn't matter where it is,
but you get.
access to those things sitting anywhere.
The key characteristics to notice like,
am I able to use it anywhere?
Am I able to use it on my mobile?
Am I able to use it?
It should be ubiquitous in nature.
That means like,
irrespective of whatever device I have,
provided the device meets the,
what do you call,
like technical specifications.
I should be able to access it.
You cannot say that like, okay,
I have a 1957 valve radio.
I am not able to use cloud computing on
that.
So that is not a valid argument here.
When I say ubiquitous,
it means like subject to the terms and
conditions of the technical,
what do you call it, compatibility.
you should be able to utilize that.
Good question. Why homogeneous?
You tell me.
Because I'm the one who is offering,
right? Like it is just a public cloud.
I'm talking about a single cloud service
provider.
So whatever I have is going to be the
same for this thing.
So like if you want to subscribe for
multiple services,
all the underlying hardware
infrastructure is going to be the same.
It is going to be my own.
offering and kind of thing.
So depending upon the type of this thing
I get,
I'm only talking about a single public
cloud provider,
multiple public cloud provider.
If you have a multi-cloud setup,
then there will be a concept of
heterogeneous infrastructure.
Now this homogeneous infrastructure,
heterogeneous infrastructure will be a
little more clearer.
when we study virtualization. Now,
why it makes sense is like...
Why it makes sense is because these
things are abstracted from us.
When you talk about homogeneous
infrastructure,
I'm talking about the type of the thing.
Some of you will get like, you know,
they call it as KVM,
some of them will be AMD,
some of them will be VMBT.
All those things are different vendors in
the mix who provide these kind of
infrastructure.
So just hold your horses a little bit.
When we talk about virtualizations,
these things will be clear.
For now,
let's assume that like what you get is
this. Now, to give you an example,
like let's say you go to a hotel and eat.
I order masala dosa.
Now the batter which comes out from that,
this thing, for me,
masala dosa at this branch is going to be
same.
But then like if I go to a party and then
order masala dosa,
the taste might be slightly different,
even though the dosa, masala dosa is same.
Why?
Because the batter comes from different
places.
Each vendor or each hotel has its own way
of grinding the batter.
Some might have a ready-made mix,
some might, you know,
do the hard work and then grind it
themselves.
Some of them would use rice flour powder
and then mix it and things like that.
Depending upon the convenience of the
provider,
the type of infrastructure which I get is
there. But ultimately,
the endpoint is like plus or minus dosa
you get it,
which is closer to homemade dosa field
which you have.
What is the closer to homemade dosa field?
Your physical hardware. I mean,
this is a very crude example, but this is.
..
what I could probably conjure up right
now. So at this point,
when we talk about homogeneous
infrastructure, let's think about,
I'm getting masala dosa.
So if I order masala dosa,
I'll get masala dosa like,
let's say from Saravana Bawa or let's say
like Bangalore different room or anything.
Now.
BTR's masala dosa would be different in
taste,
whereas Saravana Bhavans will be
different in taste. Now,
why is there difference in taste?
When we talk about virtualization
technologies,
we'll see like what ingredients those
people are using.
So there might be some different
ingredient which BTR is using because
they feel that like, okay, this is the...
cost of providing business and this is
the best optimum RAO I can get by doing
this.
So that is why my dosa tastes like this.
Or I want to establish a unique precedent
in this industry and then I offer it this
way. Something like that.
So that when we do virtualization,
we will do it. But for now,
let's stick to it.
to only masal dosa and enjoy our
breakfast.
Yeah, Sunday morning and breakfast, right?
Like good time to have masala dosa rather
than like sitting cloud computing and
chilling out.
Yes, as I said, like, it doesn't matter,
dedicated host or like anything is like
you're booking your own coach.
Like in the IRCTC example I gave,
you can take a train,
you can go the KUMBHARE in the
underserved coach,
and then like you can fight your way
inside the coach and then do this thing,
that is up to you.
Or you can book your own.
I think most of you must have read in the
recent paper, right?
Like somebody booked a,
chatted an entire coach and did Havan
inside the coach for some marriage
ceremony or something like that and
things like that.
So that is again a gross violation of
this thing. The security is breached.
Now you see, like it has got very good.
what you call similarity to cloud.
You booked this thing, you do a haven,
and if something happens,
you are compromising the other passengers
who are not connected to your coach,
but the other coaches. Imagine,
God forbid,
if a big fire or something happened when
you are having that, what do you call,
like Pooja ceremony inside the coach.
This is what I said is a shared
responsibility model in cloud.
When you go onto the cloud,
people tend to think, hack,
nothing will happen.
Like I own this infrastructure. No,
that is a mistake which we will do.
You are given an indexing,
which for today's or the period of
contract is yours to use.
But that doesn't warrant you to say like,
okay, I will do anything. I will load the,
you know.
Any software which opens or, you know,
not follow to the ADHAR, or like,
you know, established best practices,
et cetera.
So that is what I said.
You can consume anything,
any service which you want,
and yet it can be public or private or a
mixture of both.
Now the opposite of public is a private
cloud infrastructure that is exclusively
dedicated to a single organization.
Now let's tone down from public
organizations to the buses which IT
companies provide.
So many of the IT companies have buses or
cabs.
So as a, what do you call,
an employee of a different organization,
I cannot flag this thing or I cannot book
or I cannot reserve this thing, right?
Why?
Because this service is only exclusively
dedicated to a single organization.
So what I'm talking about public and
private here.
respects only with the mode of
consumption of this thing.
I can still access the same thing.
Now a private.
setup can also rely on public
infrastructure. For example,
like Infosys can outsource the public
carrying facility to this thing.
Like here in Pune,
I have seen many times Infosys and the
other companies make use of the Pune.
public transport buses.
So sometimes you see the public transport
buses on contract with this thing.
So effectively, what are you doing?
You're taking a public resource,
but making that public resource available
only to a private sector of folks.
That is also possible.
That's why I said it is going to be
confusing. Now, typically,
when you go out and then when you see
your...
BMTC, PMCC,
or Bangalore Transport Corporation,
Chennai Transport Corporation,
you all feel like, okay, this is public.
But some organizations can reserve it.
Some schools will reserve it for trips
and things like that.
So what they are doing,
they are getting some service from a
public cloud service provider.
but they are access locking it.
How are they doing?
They're access locking it in the sense
like you cannot have this service for
everybody.
You need to fit into certain criteria.
What is that criteria?
You must be a part of this particular
organization.
That will be the first basic criteria.
And then if there are subsequent criteria,
then that will keep adding.
But the basic criteria is like it is not
for everybody.
It is only for a particular set of
employees of a particular organization.
So when organization says like, okay,
I want to restrict cloud access,
not for everybody,
but like I want to create a safe space
for my organization, I'll add
extra controls, access mechanism, etc.
That is called a private cloud. Now,
here again,
when we said about public cloud service,
we said like it cannot be managed by this
thing.
You can have it in a way that like either
you take it from a public service
provider or you create your own public
infrastructure in the sense like
on-premise you set up or like you ask for
something where
you build it up from scratch and then,
you know,
sort of harden the access for the access.
The key difference here is like this is
not going to be shared with anybody else.
It is only for members of that particular
organizations.
And of course, going with the public,
this thing and car. So if I ask you,
there is public transport available and
why do you want to shun public and then
go in your own car?
The first simple reason you say like it
is too much crowded,
there is too much of this thing. I mean,
the best example is unrealable.
Let's talk about like we live in a,
what do you call like an?
ideal state where like, you know,
the buses are on time,
there is no traffic,
the time it takes for the bus to go and
the car to go is the same and things like
that. So having said that thing,
what would you say? You would say like,
okay,
I have to depend upon the bus drivers,
providers, whims and fancies.
If I sit in the bus.
then there are like, you know,
noisy this thing.
I cannot talk about my company's things
about this thing because there is always
this chance of somebody who is listening
on to this thing.
I don't want to open unnecessary doors
and kind of thing.
So if you feel that is the case,
then you go for private cloud. Even today,
I think I mentioned it in the first class.
Many of the people, I mean,
this is the irony and this is the way
businesses, people like, you know,
Microsoft and things like that pushed
other retailers to use their
infrastructure over Amazon's AWS
infrastructure, citing that,
saying that like, okay,
Amazon is also in the business of
e-commerce.
And they supply to major retailers.
So if you see worldwide,
most kind of retailers, big retailers,
shun away from Amazon's service and then
log on to the other bandwagon.
Like it's as if, you know,
what do you call it?
Like they have the saying, right?
It is the classic case of the pot.
calling the kettle black.
Nobody is good or nobody is bad in this
kind of scenario.
Everybody is there for one reason,
to increase their business.
Amazon will say like, okay,
I'm not going to do this thing.
Yes,
you can have it on premise also and it is
a private this thing. That is like,
you know,
the most private version of what you can
have.
So if you have it on on premise with your
own LAN and things like that,
then it becomes extremely secure for this
thing.
That is like a classic example of the
company having their own buses.
and then nobody else can access those
buses.
The buses are differentiated and only
employees of that particular organization
can use those SOURABH.
So that's a difference between public and
private cloud.
Now comes the concept of hybrid cloud.
There is nothing difference between the
reserving and everything is the
contractual term which you do it.
Only thing is like the access is public
or private. So it is just like the bus.
I use the same PMPL bus,
which is public in nature,
which is the same color,
and you reserve a bus from this thing.
So I will not be allowed to get inside
the reserved, I mean, the bus.
which is privately organized for a
company. But I can get it onto this thing.
So when I say private, public,
and things like that,
the access is restricted.
So whether you take a shared instance,
or whether you take an on provision
instance, or a reserved instance,
or the sync from the subscriber,
that's the contractual definition between
the organization and the cloud service
provider.
But the access and things will be only
available to the employees,
and you will have to have other other
thing,
like you might have a have a RSA token or
some other, like you know,
shared key which will be given to you,
only then you will be able to access this
thing.
Yeah, you can say that also.
Private is like our own carp and public
is like you have this thing,
shared this thing.
Now let's come to the hybrid cloud
example.
Let's say you are a cook in the sense,
you know,
I know I'm talking about too much of food
on Sunday,
so it's time for me also to have my
breakfast, but please bear with me.
This resonates well.
And if you are hungry,
you are most welcome to, you know.
Get your breakfast and let me know what
you're eating, so if anything interesting,
I can also join you guys. So,
when we talk about this hybrid cloud,
let's say you're organizing a feast,
a party,
and then you have contracted it to a cook,
and then the cook comes in, he makes,
and then you have a deal with the cook.
See, I'm expecting...
500 guests to be there in the party
evening, so please prepare the dish.
And the cook is the most renowned guy and
things like that.
Now what happens is suddenly you find out
that like in your calculations,
you did some mistake. So instead of 500,
the total count was coming to 750.
So, normally,
when you tell the cook and things like
that,
they will actually have an adjustment for,
like, you know, not more than like,
you know, 50 to 100 max to max.
They'll say, like, okay, plus or minus,
like if 100 people come in, fine,
I'll be still able to manage,
we'll pull through,
but all of a sudden you are increasing it
by twenty-five percent and say, like,
okay.
The count has exceeded the initial thing.
And now instead of 500 people,
there are going to be 750 people who's
going to land. What do I do now?
So, let's say.
There are two options,
like in real world scenario,
what happens is like the sambar becomes a
little more runny, you add water,
you add this thing and things like that.
But here, the cook is like, you know,
a very decent guy.
He's very ethical in nature and things
like that.
So he doesn't do all that backdoor
activities.
So he doesn't want to spoil his
reputation.
So what is the best thing he do?
He has his own catering service outside
also, which keeps catering for this thing.
So he will go and say like, okay,
I tied up, I don't have capacity.
Let me go and buy the same this thing
from this particular hotel,
which I know for sure.
That's the same quality, if not like,
you know, not to my quality,
but like slightly better, I mean,
slightly lower grade or slightly higher
grade. Let me go and buy this thing.
Because I just need to order 150 more
dishes to serve my existing capability.
Now,
this action in cloud terminology is
called as bursting, right?
We call them as cloudbursting.
When you say cloudbursting,
it means sudden, immediate.
spike has happened on your resource
demand. Like for example,
like in the cook example I gave you,
the guests have come in and it has
overwhelmed you. Similarly,
on your workload instance,
there can be cases where multiple people
come in and then the demand increases.
And if you are not able to scale.
or like you have not anticipated this and
then you have not enabled scaling,
then you can go and then get it outside
the service area. So like for example,
you can route the traffic to some other
provider so that like the requests are
served.
The objective of doing this in any
ecosystem, cloud,
non-cloud or things like that is like.
to get your workload done, right?
So how you do it,
how the end user perceives it is not a
material. How you manage is this thing.
So the perception of providing the end
user the ability to do their tasks,
et cetera, will do.
And if you're in a mission critical
system, like you're running a business,
and if your business fails.
It happens everywhere.
Remember a couple of years back, America,
sorry, Amazon's big billion days,
it crashed.
Flipkart's big billion days crashed. Why?
Suddenly you'll see like all of a sudden
there is a huge spike which comes up.
It is going to overwhelm all their
servers and everything is going to go.
In the flashlight,
everything is going to go down.
And what does that mean?
What does that translate to?
Once it crashes,
then immediately you will open your
Instagram and say, like, okay, man,
this Flipkart sucks. It doesn't open.
It doesn't do this thing.
You are screwing up Flipkart's image.
Flipkart's brand image is gone. Similar,
I'm not taking the names or the things.
Some companies' brand image is gone.
What happens is like,
and that spreads like wildfire.
In this age of connected social media,
what happens is like,
it doesn't take that much of time for
these reels and memes to
reach the entire world.
And everybody knows that and people who
are also planning to do this thing will
say like, okay, forget it now,
like there is no point.
So potential revenue loss is also there.
So that is why when you plan your cloud
infrastructure or your cloud workload and
things like that,
if you talk about this DevOps infra
engineer and things like that,
they'll always be on their toes,
especially during these bulk season,
peak season,
because one slip and then like it becomes
a pain point right from the CXO. I mean,
if you have not met your CEO,
all the C-level people,
one instance it takes to meet all of them.
Yes, you're right, Bhumika.
You can do a scale up on this thing
provided you have a contract. So,
I'm not sure like whether on the fly,
I think even now cloud providers are
trying to bring in that,
but like it is better if you have some
sort of agreement so that like you do it.
It is just like okay.
you going into a new hotel and say like,
okay, I need these things.
That guy will look at you suspiciously.
But if the cook goes and says like, okay,
bye,
send it means like he knows the cook and
everything and then he'll send it, PK,
I'll collect it from this person,
I know him.
So we already have a sort of
understanding between them.
Obviously,
they will charge like this is the
business in cloud, right?
How many of you have in the early days of
cloud? I myself have run into, you know,
several $100 of worth of this,
and then we were all learning. Now,
the same thing has translated into AI and
things like that, like people are still...
struggling to get a grip on the tokens
usage and things like that.
So every new technology has its own set
of challenges for us to overcome.
And it is these nitty-gritty challenges
that the cloud providers try to exploit.
As I said, it's a valid question. Now,
how much would you anticipate for
scalability? Like,
nobody provisions unlimited scalability.
So they will say, like, okay,
this much of cluster is there.
But these kind of situations,
to answer your question,
we are all prepared
for a rainy day. We have bikes,
we have rain coats, we have this thing.
But when we are prepared for a rainy day,
monsoon time,
if the average rainfall during this thing
is like, you know,
let's say 100 millimeter during the
entire season, we are prepared for that.
But if, let's say,
200 millimeter of rain occurs in 2
minutes of time.
How much ever preparedness you make,
you will not be able to do this.
You're going to be flooded with this
thing.
So you need to have better preparation in
terms of water clearance, dam, this thing,
evacuation plants and things like that
set up in this thing. Similarly,
When historically and things like that,
it is very difficult to face.
So scaling of model will work to an
extent,
but like what happens if your scale model
is not sufficient to handle the existing
load?
So this is about the three types of
models in the cloud system.
So like public, private, and hybrid.
Remember, public is for everyone,
private is for a designated set of
organization,
and hybrid is a setup which can be
migrated on DHIMAN.
So you can have a public cloud service
and then get something from public.
You can have a private cloud service and
get from a public.
Or you can have, you know, a mix of both.
Now,
the last one is a Community Cloud model,
which is the example of MetroZip.
For those of you who are in Pune and
things like that,
there is a service called as MetroZip
where organizations around the Hinjewadi
area have subscribed to a.
A company called Metro Zip,
and then they offer transport service,
so it is neither public nor private,
but it is like in between.
What do you mean by in between?
Only the employees of the subscribing
organization,
so the Metro Zip will offer services to,
let's say, Infosys, TCS, Deloitte, ENY,
and things like that, which are...
Situated in and around the Hinjewadi area,
so if you are an employee of these
organizations and you have subscribed to
this service, you do it. Now,
you might ask why you require this
earlier when cloud computing was in its
nascent format and things like that,
you wanted to create a separate.
differentiation so that people could work
together on like-minded projects and
share between organizations,
this community cloud setup was created.
Nowadays,
with the advent and technological
advances in public and private cloud
infrastructure,
these kinds of community clouds have sort
of
you know, taken a back seat.
So we will just focus only on the things.
The earliest example of community cloud
was the Sun, the center for some day,
they were studying that the world's
biggest collider project,
Haldron collider project in Switzerland,
which they built.
That is a scientific community.
And that scientific community was funded
and worked by scientists across the globe
from different organizations,
both public organizations and private
organizations.
So when they wanted a platform to
collaborate and then share and then
consume resources and things like that,
they created a community cloud on
OpenStack and then
They were using that cloud. Now,
since with the advancement in cloud,
with technology getting cheaper and
things like that,
this kind of community cloud instances
has sort of gone down, I would say,
but it's not like completely empty.
I don't find any.
Relevant examples of a viable community
cloud still thriving today,
unless you consider, like you know,
schools and universities which have both
schools or multiple educational
institutions and things like that,
but still they don't consider that as
community cloud because it is still.
A part of their own organizations and not
from different organizations joined
together.
OK, so these are the things.
Now, before we go...
Just give me a second.
I have created these notes and uploaded
it there on the shared drive.
So you can go through it.
So this is just like a quick reference
for you to go through the different Cloud
parameters. This is 1 here.
And.
Yeah.
So the other one is about this X86 rings,
which we will cover shortly.
So this will sort of like, you know,
answer a few critical questions which you
have some doubts about.
So the notes are present in that shared
folder which I have given this thing.
Okay.
So clear about public cloud,
private cloud,
and community and hybrid clouds.
Let's move on.
So, as somebody said in the chat, like,
who was that? He said, like, yeah,
Anupriya has mentioned that, like,
everybody is moving to multi-cloud.
It's a very valid statement. Well said,
Anupriya, and it is a fact nowadays.
Take us, for example, like,
forget all the cloud and things like that.
How many of you have more than one OTT?
I mean, I should ask the question,
how many of you have only one OTT
subscription?
That will be easier to answer.
Most of us will have to like Netflix,
Amazon Prime or Netflix, Amazon Prime Z.
Why? Because like,
even if you don't want a multiple
subscription,
you take a phone and then you go on to a
plan and then that fellow will bundle
something and give you take this plan.
499 car recharge will give you one year
worth of ZP, Sony, blah, blah,
blah kind of bouquet of channel offerings.
So multi-cloud is earlier when cloud was
there,
I'm talking about 8 to 10 years back when
cloud was in its nascent form.
Things were pretty complex,
people were trading with caution and
things like that.
Multi-cloud concept was not there.
So it all again depended on the
experience you get. So word of mouth.
So earlier I would say like, okay,
I'll go with cloud provider A.
He gives me these, these, these features.
It was great and things like that.
Somebody will come and say like, no, no,
no, no, I had a bad experience.
Let me use this. He's a new player.
He's offering it cheaper.
and things like that.
Can you share the screen what you are
seeing, PRAJAKTA,
so I can see because that was the link
which was shared by one of the student to
say that like, okay,
please upload it here.
E.
So coming to the multi-cloud,
multi-cloud means, like as I said,
multiple cloud service providers at a
single instance. Why?
Because we go by the traditional
investment advice that is like we don't
carry all our, I mean,
we don't put all our eggs in one basket,
meaning risk mitigation. Tomorrow,
If something happens to our cloud service
provider, God forbid,
like he becomes rogue and says like, okay,
I'm going to hold you hostage, just like,
you know, this thing. It is there.
Then what happens to your this thing?
You cannot be held at the mercy of
somebody else,
pointing a gun at you and saying like,
okay, if you want to,
utilize these resources,
then you will have to pay additional 25%.
At that point, you will be like, you know,
hard pressed not to give in to his
demands,
because if you don't run your business,
loss is much more than what you would be
paying him.
So to factor in that kind of things,
I mean, it's not that like, okay, I mean,
don't get the idea saying like, okay.
This is a good business model where I'll
come as a cloud service provider and then
keep threatening my this thing host.
I'm not saying that,
but anything can happen these days.
You must have seen the cases of the
JetBlue incidents or like one of those
airlines who had their entire business
operation shut down for half a day.
I mean,
even though it was not purposefully or
malicious intent in nature,
it was a pure genuine operational issue
where some infrastructure issue.
broke the back of the cloud service
provider,
and which in turn cascaded down to the
main consumer. Now,
had they had a backup plan or things like
that,
they could have switched their core
ticketing system,
check-in system to those things,
even though if not all of that.
But that is a lesson learned,
and then probably they would have taken
corrective steps. Why don't you do it?
How many of you in office like these days
we work from home and things like that?
And I'm not sure like they would say like
the first question when you fill out the
request for you know submitting a hybrid
kind of a work mode, they'll say like,
okay,
what is the type of connection you have?
Do you have any backup plan and things
like that?
Most of us would have said like, okay,
we have a phone and we have a broadband
at home.
Now what happens if your ISP also goes
down and Airtel or the mobile phone also
goes down?
So, you are doomed, right? Like,
in the sense, like,
either you will have to convince your
manager to request him this thing,
because...
The first thing which we say is like,
how many times will that happen?
The cloud has given us a false sense of
security saying like, okay, we are,
I mean,
it's not a false sense of security.
The technological advances have made it
clear that like, it'll be there.
We all use Gmail.
How can you recollect how many times you
were not able to access your Gmail?
It's always there.
The service is always there.
And even if it had gone down,
probably you might not even have noticed
that like, okay,
the service outage was there.
So the security is always there,
but that is why if you see the cloud
service providers, SLA,
the agreement which they say is like 99.
999%.
They never say 100% because then it is
open to legal issues and they are able to
be sued because there is always the off
chance that like with whatever measures
they put in,
there are going to be a point, not, not,
not one percentage off chance that like,
okay, I'm going to fail.
So given this premise,
what people do is like they say, like,
okay,
let me take a backup for core services in
another cloud provider and then have some
instances created.
So that will be my secondary and the same.
Of course, it is a cost of doing business.
So like, if normally ask people,
do you think like, okay,
I have a broadband at home from airport?
And let's say you have some other company,
let's say KATTA Play is also offering you
the same.
How many of us will think to take, okay,
I'll let me take KATTA also as backup in
case something happens?
None of us will do because why?
You have to pay for both simultaneously.
But when you answer the question saying
like, okay,
if there is something wrong with Airtel.
And if I'm not able to connect for 30
minutes,
what is the loss to my productivity or
what happens to my productivity?
How much of income am I going to lose?
If that exceeds a certain thing,
then it makes sense for you to have this
thing.
And it makes sense for organizations
because they are business entities,
they are enterprises.
Their main this thing is to work,
and then, like,
they cannot be tied up with,
what do you call, like,
gone are the days like when you say, like,
okay, now there is no power,
I'll come and look into it later. So,
that era is over. Now, everybody expects,
what do you call, like, instant response.
So, like, for example, if you say,
I want it to be done instantly,
the moment.
you utter the word instantly,
you expect it to be done. Otherwise,
like again, the call comes in.
So the nature of the service has also
increased to a more faster,
what do you call, like closure rate.
So if you don't have multiple Cloud,
then it becomes difficult for you to
continue provider. And this is.
Like a, this thing,
like earlier it was optional.
Now more and more people are seeing the
benefits.
Going further in like in a couple of
years time with AI and adoptions and
things like that, this will be like,
you know, standard practice.
Right.
Now coming to the advantages and
disadvantages,
you have a negotiating leverage.
So if one cloud service provider suddenly
tends to increase this thing,
then you have the option to go and
negotiate with your contemporary this
thing. So that is there.
Then you have the best of the breed
services, like if one fails,
you can go into this thing.
Resilience and redundancy,
the regulatory flexibility,
but on the other hand,
when you talk about disadvantages,
switching between cloud operators is like,
we'll again come into the issue of that
masala dosa taste.
You were having a good taste with one
this thing, but when you go off,
suppose you're paying something low.
I'm assuming like, you know,
that guy gives you a cheaper version of
the doser.
So it will take some time to get
acclimatized to those kind of things.
So that operational complexity is there.
Networking and cost, inconsistency,
security and IAM. I mean, obviously,
the way you're going to skin a cat is
going to be different in different
organizations. So
all the operational complexities of
managing this thing. For example,
I don't know how many of you in your
professional life have worked with teams
other than your own organizations.
So people who work in GCC kind of centers
are forced to work with different vendors,
right? Like for example,
like you might work with...
Company A, Company B, Company C,
Company D, and things like that.
So you know the difficulty of having
streamlining data across those kind of,
now what do you call it, like...
Right.
So each one has its own quirks and other
things associated with it.
It becomes a question of familiarity.
Even in your own organization,
let's say you have been working in a team
right from, let's say you are a fresher,
you joined the college,
you and a batch of five friends.
Join together in the organization. Now,
when you go into this organization,
what happens is like you tend to gel well
with you on this thing rather than the
other other thing.
It will take some time for you to gel
well with coworkers and things like that.
Why?
Because of the familiarity of the thing,
the bonding which you shared and the
relationship which you shared.
from college days carries over. Similarly,
when you subscribe to a single crowd
provider and then moving it,
there are ways,
mechanisms and things like that,
even though cloud is trying to make it
standardized so that like with the
software defined environment, SDEs,
I would say,
what has happened is like everything is
software controlled. So.
You just don't need to know the
abstraction. I mean,
you are abstracted from the hard workings
of the technology behind. But still,
getting to know what it is, how it is,
and things like that, takes some time.
And that is the complexity involved here.
Because like here,
you're talking about something which you
don't see physically, which is like,
you know, a virtual entity behind a wall.
Okay, I'll upload it here. No worries.
Now,
let's move on to the final this thing.
This is going to be a easy, quick.
So first thing is like,
we said like 3 service models,
4 deployment models,
and now we have 5 essential
characteristics of Cloud Computing. Now,
what are the five essential
characteristics?
First one is on-demand self-service.
Second one is ubiquitous network access.
Third one is like location transparent
resource pooling.
Fourth one is rapid elasticity.
Fifth one is like pay-per-use or measured
service.
I don't think I need to explain these
things, but still on-demand self-service,
I've been talking from day one,
meaning whenever I'm in the mood for it,
I go and then switch it on. For example,
Today,
I want to watch Netflix in the morning.
So I go switch it on.
Netflix should not say like, okay,
why this is the time for Cloud Computing
class.
You should be sitting in the class and
listening to the lecture and not going to
Netflix and doing this. No,
Netflix doesn't do that.
So anytime I choose,
I want to watch Netflix.
I mean, that is, yes, there are companies,
my own company does that. Like they have,
we have our own private cloud and in case
of emergencies and exigencies for some of
the verticals,
we do take from a partner that is AWS.
So that is always there.
So that is on-demand self-service.
It doesn't matter anytime,
any other thing of day.
So this is where the 99.999% SLA comes in.
When they say it is available for you at
any given point of time, it is available.
No questions asked. Now,
if they don't provide you that committed
SLA, then you are...
likely to sue them and then like lawsuits
happen and things like that.
Ubiquitous network access, as I said,
it doesn't matter whether you use a phone,
whether you use a laptop,
or whether you use a desktop,
or whether you use a virtual machine
itself from a private host to access this
thing. It doesn't matter.
Only criteria being your hardware should
match the basic requirements which is set,
and then it should...
have that kind of capability to access
that. It is just like, okay.
How do I put it like?
Anybody can learn. That is a this thing.
We say like, okay, education is for all.
But now if I'm saying like I'm teaching a
calculus class and then if a fifth
standard or like a third standard student
comes in and says like,
I don't understand calculus and things
like that,
I first have to teach him functions from
functions. He has to understand limits.
then he has to understand integration,
differentiation, and then put together,
we go into the calculus mode.
Without that,
it is not going to be possible.
So similarly,
you should scale up to certain basic
requirements checklist,
which they have provided,
and then say like, okay,
my device is compatible for this,
so mobile, yes, I'll be able to access.
TV, yes,
I'll be able to access provided I have
these things. Laptop, yes,
workstation here.
Location transparent resource pooling.
So this location where the servers are
given, it doesn't matter.
All you need will get is an endpoint.
You connect to the endpoint.
How the services are shared and things
like that is the provider's headache,
and then you don't get those details.
It is just like a cab aggregator to your
company. He might have
different cabs running across the city.
Now,
if Infosys requires a cab from going from
point A to point B,
they call the service provider.
So he will call a resource which is
closer to that particular location and
assign it because the time it takes to
reach there will be short. Now,
Infosys will not bother saying like, okay,
I want this place or that place.
That will come later when there are
issues with the provider,
so they'll say like, "Okay,
the guys coming from this place is always
violent.
I want a person who is sober who has
passed these checks,
so then the cost increases,
so that is what this GDPR and this data
provisioning kind of things has happened
because of that,
what has happened now is like...
You cannot have this location transparent
kind of thing.
So you will have to have an established
location where this confirms by the cloud
provider, okay,
this is staying within Europe only.
It doesn't go outside Europe.
Or for government of US government data,
it doesn't go outside continental US and
things like that.
Rapid elasticity, as we mentioned earlier,
is the concept of scaling up fast.
So scale up and down.
Today I need 10 computers because I'm
working on a startup idea.
I have 10 people coming in. I've done it.
Now,
tomorrow my startup idea click and then
100 more people are joining,
so I need 100 more resources.
Yes, done. Everything is done instantly.
Imagine this in the previous thing.
You'll be spending half a month or like,
you know,
more than a month just to get the
hardware set up.
You'll have to negotiate with the vendor,
you have to book a price,
then you'll have to have it shipped,
installed, and then like set up.
But now everything is like, you know,
at the speed of thought.
So you think about it and then it is done.
And finally, obviously,
it all comes with a cost. Earlier,
like it was a one-time cost,
but now for every service which you use
or don't use,
you keep paying for this thing.
So that is the flip side of using cloud,
but yes, the benefits outweigh the cost,
and you'll have to be prudent in.
Cost management as well.
So these are the five essential
characteristics of Cloud Computing.
So this is the notes analysis and things
which I just explained,
so I'll just skim through it faster.
You can read through it in the slide,
like in just text.
No, no, no. Rapid elasticity is correct.
Users came suddenly.
On-demand self-service is like,
it is just like going to the ATM.
You go to the ATM when you need cash.
That's it.
So when I need to use the resource,
I just go there.
Rapid elasticity means like when the,
to give the same example,
like what happens is like,
demonetization happened and you know the
entire mohalla is at the ATM counter.
So the ATM is going to run out of cash.
So you need to have another ATM set up
there.
So you need to scale up fast so that to
give this thing.
So on-demand self-service is you
initiating the transaction or you
initiating the invocation of the cloud
service which you want to utilize.
The advantages of Cloud,
I don't need to tell you.
The costs are reduced.
You have ease of utilization,
quality of service,
high availability and reliability.
You have low entry barrier,
outsourced IT management,
and things like that.
All these are the thing.
I hope you all seen that this thing,
right, like HR.
A recruitment like video,
so cloud ecosystem is both a bane and a
boon.
It gives you the best flexibilities and
things like that,
provided you are willing to give up
certain bad habits and traits coming from
an on-premise environment. Here,
you have to be very, very...
careful about what service you are using,
when you are using,
how much you are using and things like
that because it is metered by use and
then nobody will explicitly tell you like,
okay, you are using these things.
So you have to make use of certain
billing agents and other alerts to alert
you constantly on how much your costs you
are incurring and things like that.
Some of the cloud failures which I have
mentioned here.
Just to give you a reality check,
saying that like, okay, nobody is,
what do you call like, punitive in this,
this thing, like you are,
you cannot say like, okay,
I'm a cloud service provider and then
like, I'm immune to outage.
You might be the Google,
you might be the Amazons of this world,
but still.
Like if disaster strikes, it strikes.
How much ever you do the backup planning,
how much ever you do, what do you call,
like session management between regions
and raw locations,
backups and things like that.
Something happens, it happens.
And if you're all, ultimately,
these are all like, you know, computer,
the thing. Simple reason can be like.
you know,
hardware failures and things like that
can happen at any given point of time.
So if your replacement technology or like
policy out runs the way components are
failing or like disaster strikes,
then you are in for a big major outage.
Water.
Can you be specific, BHANU,
on the question how cybersecurity
challenges are adhered to in the sense
like it is?
Let me just allow your mic so it will be
easy.
Hello!
Go ahead.
Yeah, good morning.
Good morning, sir.
Good one.
So,
I'm asking that there are something
disaster happened in the past. Recently,
we talked about the Air India,
Mm.
where Air India, the credit cards,
that data has been caused and where the
major blood have happened. So, similarly,
some other incidents also happened.
For the data breach,
I'm talking about the data breach or the
Mhm.
cloud,
either it could be a public cloud or a
private cloud. Okay, so that data breach,
out of data breach can be controlled or
restricted, or it could be not restricted,
I can say.
How could it be minimized to further that?
The such incident should not be so that
companies have to be aware of higher,
higher, higher financial loss in that.
Yeah.
Yeah, good question. Yes, yes,
I got your question.
Hope you got my question.
And the answer to your question is in you
only.
Okay, before I answer your question,
I hope you're all married and then have
kids who are going to school and things
like that, right? So what do we do?
We tell our children when you go into the
bus and things like that,
don't talk to strangers.
If somebody gives you a chocolate or this
thing, you should not say this thing.
You should not talk to strangers unless
somebody else in the group knows it and
things like that.
So what are we trying to inculcate or
instill there?
We are trying to instill a framework of
safety for the child.
So when we talk about cloud applications
and things like that,
You have the this thing is provided by
the cloud, AWS and things,
and the rest of the half is the person
who is using it. Now,
when we go to the this thing school on a
public transport on trains,
the trains will have given you safety and
enrollment and this thing like.
by providing doors and things like that.
But if you choose to travel on the roof
of the train and get electrocuted and
then die, and then say like, okay,
Indian Railways is at fault,
that is what is happening with the kind
of security question.
And it's a very good question.
There is no right or wrong answer.
The only answer I can say for that is
like, there are people.
When the surface area for the attack
increases,
why do data threats or cybersecurity
attack happens? There has to be a proper,
what do you call, like gain.
Nobody is going to attack on this thing.
And if you give a large surface area to
attack, anybody can do this thing. Now,
when you're designing an application,
you should follow the best practices.
You should not have any hard-coded keys.
You should not have hard-coded
all your secrets and passwords should be
stored separately in Secrets Manager.
The way you invoke objects should be like,
you know, what do you call,
like the single responsibility principle,
like one object will work on one thing.
Why are those rules set in?
You don't follow just because somebody
out of a blue thought that this is what
it is.
So the security best practices and things
like that, every organization
does these things.
First thing is like they have the policy
defined. Second thing is like training.
Every organization who are working with
cloud will have periodic assessment of
their employees saying like, okay,
are you doing this thing?
And then the training is inculcated into
their system.
So it becomes a part of this DNA.
There is no magic button like a service
saying like, okay, cybersecurity on.
I just switch it on and then do this
thing. No,
we have tools and technologies to prevent
this thing.
Like you have policies on cloud. Now,
if you open all ports accessible anywhere,
that is a violation which you are doing.
The cloud service provider cannot do
anything in spite of saying,
1000 times, like, okay, please be careful.
If you just, it's the same thing,
like you have your house,
you leave your door open and then go
outside without locking it.
And then come back and say, like, okay,
society,
I'm living in a very gated society.
How can somebody come and then do the
same? Yes,
the gated society will do certain things,
but like,
If there is a the thing, like, you know,
us.
I got, I got that.
VIVEK.
I got the question,
question one over question or to this,
Yeah.
so my question is that is there is there
an ITL or software LDC lifecycle that so
did we have any guidelines?
Or they have given certain what we call
it a rule framework that is this is a
technique that we have to adopt,
so if we are agreeing not agreeing to it,
then we are having certain compliance on
that. Who has this protocol?
Yes, yes, yes, yes,
they do check it when your workload is
onboarded onto the cloud.
There will be two level checks,
which is normally done.
One is by your internal IT assessment
team, the what do you call like...
My is slightly different,
my is slightly different. Sorry,
my is slightly different, so that I know.
So, every year there is, for example,
Mhm.
cloud every day the audit has been done,
right? Audit has to be done, so in audit.
Yeah.
We have certain criteria, right? So,
if that criteria is given by IT or any IT
body, so that we need to be there,
they could be a tolerance that it should
be within that limit.
If it is diverted from both,
then it is a compliant.
You got my what I need to say?
Yeah, so go ahead.
What's the question now?
My question is that, for example,
just like I am talking about small system
plans, right? UK has a soft system plan,
right?
Mhm.
And Australia also follows them for the
cyber security.
But do we have it in India also because
the data breacher cases are more over in
India rather than other reasons we are
talking about.
If talking to a bank or anyone like that,
there are less, less disruptions or less,
but in case of a so is there is there any
protocol or any audit audit compliance or
audit criteria?
To put cocol that needs to be there,
if there is a deviation,
then it needs to be a bit cautious. Yeah,
that is my question.
I'm not see apart standard safety
security or security policies which
prevents VAPT and other intrusion
detection things,
I'm not aware of any this thing because
it is a constantly evolving this thing.
So it just keeps getting updated as per a
new this thing because we are.
In A perennially react mode in this area,
we cannot gauge it. We can only say like,
okay,
I'm going to protect my this thing as far
as possible. If there are something,
some loopholes happens, that is why like,
you know, people keep releasing patches,
right?
Like otherwise they would have just
released once at one point of time and
then done.
There is another loophole coming,
another patch is released,
another loophole coming,
another patch is released. So.
I'm not sure,
I'll have to check on this thing if there
is any standard set of policies except
from the normal VAPT security,
the port access, you know,
network hardening,
all those standard security policies
which every company uses on their behalf.
So that I'll check and then get back to
you.
Thank you so much. I got an answer.
Thank you.
OK, so now these are some, you know,
thinking points.
for you to think.
And what I want you to do is like each
one of you to write these answers.
It can be short answers.
Why do you think cloud is a boon or a
bane? Boon means like it is a blessing,
it's a good thing,
or a bane means like it's a curse.
What is your trust level of any cloud you
use?
I want you to give a short example of why
do you trust your cloud.
What do you understand by a hosted
application, cloud enabled, cloud native,
cloud agnostic?
Don't use ChatGPT or any of those AI
tools.
I want you to make a sincere assessment
of your understanding and then you can
just share it with me here.
So this is just a sort of a mini exercise
to recap on the cloud readiness and
preparedness,
which we go ahead when we talk about
cloud.
Okay.
You don't have to write it here,
you can just, you know, mail it to me.
Is your mail ID updated on the trailer
hotel?
Open this.
I'm just typing. Yeah,
I'm just typing it here.
Hello?
So, really,
so these all will be updated in the point
also, right?
This question will be updated in paper.
I can do it on the SharePoint also.
Yeah, yeah. So, because, okay,
that will be fine.
All right.
So now we move on from the basics
nitpicking to sentence formation in Cloud.
So this session and the next couple of
sessions will be dedicated to
virtualization. But before we go,
I forgot to mention,
so we had a discussion with Professor
Murali Sir,
who is the lead faculty for this
particular course.
And this is regarding your first
assignment, first quiz.
So,
the first quiz we decided is like to keep
it in the first week of September before
the SINGH, and there will be 2 quizzes.
It would be in the first week prior to
your midsem,
and then after midsem there will be
another quiz. So,
the first quiz chapter will be all these
topics which we cover,
like probably introduction to cloud and
virtualization,
because I think that's all the time we
would have to cover.
And then the other topics which we cover
till the first week of October will be
there for the second quiz.
It will be a very short and sweet quiz
for five marks. So you will have,
as I mentioned earlier,
you will have time to do it.
It will be like, you know,
a little bit limited in nature, but
You will have sufficient time to complete
that,
so don't worry about the timings and
things like that.
Okay,
so now what we need to understand is like
what is virtualization?
What is the x86 architecture?
What is approaches to virtualization,
applications of virtualization?
Then we will move on to the heart and
soul of virtualization,
which is called as a VMM or hypervisor.
Now, before even I go into this,
can anybody tell me what is
virtualization based on the topics?
I know we have been talking basic to
advanced, advanced to basic,
things like that.
The nature of the course is like that,
so that we keep jumping up and on.
Simple sir, Arsalan,
what is virtualization?
Can anybody tell quickly type?
Chat fingers up.
Same hardware, multiple OS.
I can have one laptop and have a dual
boot installed, so that is virtualization.
That this is to be hosted virtualization
is virtual machine, nope.
Virtual version of physical computer. OK,
one machine working as multiple machines,
software acting as a hardware buffering.
One restaurant with multiple chefs to
cook many dishes.
Interesting.
Provisioning a box where we have always
installed and we can use server like AVD,
okay?
Making resource available on the internet,
but that is a job of cloud, right?
Making resource available on the internet.
Virtualization means everything running
on virtual world.
Yeah, because of this.
Tenant oldest tech sharing resources set
up in 1950.
I was just being students,
you guys didn't give me the oldest answer
of virtualization. I'm like,
you go and then told your friends, like,
okay, I'm present, present,
attendance sign, right? Even though...
Even though you are not present there,
but you have still signed up for this
thing.
Right,
all of you are very well versed and it
gives, I mean,
it's heartening to know that like you
have it.
Please, I mean,
the reason for asking this thing is like,
you know,
it clears out certain misconceptions also.
Don't say that like, you know,
everything is on the net in a virtual
mode is virtualization and things like
that. Yes,
it is a virtualized resource which you
are accessing.
It is the end result of something which
has happened.
By somebody giving you action and things
like that,
and that is what you are seeing on the
net or consuming using the net,
but that doesn't mean it is
virtualization. Virtualization,
as many of you have said with restaurant
examples and things like that,
plain simple factor is...
you are taking an existing physical
resource.
The physical resource need not be just
CPU, it can be memory, it can be network,
it can be this thing. And then...
By some means, magic layer,
you are creating multiple instances of
different kinds of, like for example,
the basic example which you have is like,
I have a simple laptop and I have a
software called as a hypervisor which
runs on top of that.
Using that hypervisor.
I'll be able to create multiple guest
images or operating system,
which will entirely behave as an
individual PC.
So it is just like I have one, this thing,
and then I multiply that one into four,
and then those four are shared amongst
people.
Yeah,
Docker is a very advanced level of
virtualization. We'll come to that.
Clones,
not necessarily because virtual machines,
you cannot call clones of the same
because they run different operating
system than of the parent.
So it's not a clone.
It is just like emulation.
We call them as guests.
That will be a more apt term.
Okay, now before we begin, right, like...
No, no, WSL is not virtualization.
WSL is what aids virtualization.
And for the others,
WSL is just like Windows Subsystem for
Linux. Please,
let's not go into those things.
That is what has enabled, you know,
Dockers and other things to come into
picture.
So I will not answer any questions on WSL
and things.
I don't want to confuse the others.
We will.
take that in time due course when we talk
about Dockers. But no, WSL is a tool.
It is just a, what do you call,
like a technology which has enabled you
to run Dockers on Windows platform. Now.
This will be your first lab course also.
Your lab facilitators will come and then
talk to you about this and they'll give
you the lab sheets and things like that.
But you can follow this video.
I have uploaded this video on that
OneDrive portal also.
You can review it later at a convenience.
But let's today go through this.
There are a few, you know, terms,
new terms which will come up,
which we'll have to understand first
before we go into this thing. So just,
you know,
let me know if you're hearing the audio
on this.
Hey guys,
in this video I'm going to show you how
you can download and install.
Are you able to hear the audio?
Okay, great.
So this is just going to take under 10,
15 minutes of your time.
So just watch this.
Some of you are familiar with this thing,
so I request you to please bear with the
others. So like we are a big team here.
There are multiple people from multiple
backgrounds, so please be considerate.
Do not jump the gun.
Now is the time for like.
I know those who know to have your masal
dosas and come takes 10 minutes quickly
have this in the others.
Please pay attention because your
understanding of these key terms is more
important as we go along because we would
be just referring to them constantly in
the subsequent classes. Tall Ubuntu 20.
04 on.
Your VirtualBox in your Windows Ten
operating system. So,
those of you who don't know what
VirtualBox is,
VirtualBox is a tool which will enable
you to run different operating systems
virtually on your host operating system.
So, in this case...
My host operating system is Windows 10,
and I have installed VirtualBox on my
Windows 10,
and then this VirtualBox will enable me
to run different operating systems
virtually on my Windows 10 operating
system. Now,
if you don't know how to install
VirtualBox.
You just need to search for VirtualBox on
your favorite browser,
and the first link which will appear here
will be from VirtualBox.org,
so just click on this link,
and once this link opens,
you just need to click on the downloads
link here,
and you will be able to see this kind of
interface.
Just click on the Windows Host option
here, and you will see that VirtualBox.
exe will be downloaded,
and once it's downloaded,
you just need to install it. So,
the installation process is really easy,
so I'm not going to go through the
installation process of VirtualBox.
You just need to click some next buttons.
And VirtualBox will be installed on your
Windows operating system. So,
once you have installed VirtualBox on
your Windows operating system,
it's going to look like this,
and whenever you open VirtualBox,
it's going to open Oracle VM VirtualBox
Manager. Now, we are going to download.
The ISO file which is required to install
Ubuntu on our VirtualBox. So,
for downloading the ISO file of Ubuntu,
you can just search for Ubuntu,
and the first link which will appear here
will be from Ubuntu.com. So,
I am going to just click on this link.
And straight away,
you will see this option here,
which is what's new in Ubuntu 20.04,
because 20.
04 is the latest version of Ubuntu which
is released recently,
so here you will see downloads.
Tab here,
and when you click on the download tab,
you will see the Ubuntu desktop,
so you can just click on the version
which is available,
and most probably you might want to
install the LTS version. Okay,
so make sure that whenever you install
Ubuntu, you install the...
LTS version,
LTS means the long term support version
which will at least run for two years.
Okay,
so the support will run for two years.
So I'm going to just click on Ubuntu
Desktop and here you will see the
download button.
So I'm going to just click on the
download button.
And when you click on the download button,
the ISO file will be downloaded on your
Windows operating system,
so this file is around 2.
GB file, so it will take some.
Time to download,
but I have already downloaded.
This file on my Windows operating system,
so I'm going to just cancel this download,
and also,
if you want to support Ubuntu project,
then you can just give a small donation
to Ubuntu. For now,
I don't want to do anything,
so I have just downloaded the ISO file.
So, once you have downloaded the ISO file,
it's going to look like this,
in case you have downloaded the 20.
04 version of Ubuntu. So,
the name is Ubuntu 20.04 Desktop AMD64.
iso file.
So,
once you have downloaded this ISO file,
we are ready to install Ubuntu on our
VirtualBox. So, on your VirtualBox,
you just need to click on the New button
here,
and once you click on the New button here,
you can provide the name of your new
machine. So,
my new machine name is Ubuntu,
so I'm going to just write Ubuntu here.
And let's say I will also give the
version of Ubuntu, let's say 20.04 here,
and straight away VirtualBox is smart
enough to provide you the proper options
here. Okay,
so here you will see the machine folder
where all the VirtualBox related.
Files will be downloaded and saved on
your Windows operating system,
and the type here is Linux,
because Ubuntu is a Linux-based operating
system,
and the version here is Ubuntu 64-bit,
because we have downloaded the 64-bit ISO
file.
OK,
there is no other option on the website,
as far as I know.
If you want to choose any other operating
system, the procedure is same;
you just need to select the operating
system you want to install, and here...
You can see many choices are given here.
Okay,
so type is Linux and the version is
Ubuntu 64 bit, and then click on next.
And here in the memory size,
I generally provide the memory up to the
green mark, so up to here, whatever.
Is allowed on my Windows operating system
at this point, and then I click on next.
Here, just leave everything as default,
so just leave it as default,
and then click on the Create button. Now,
here, hard disk file type,
just leave it as VDI,
which is VirtualBox Disk Image,
and then click on next.
And here also,
you just need to leave this as
dynamically allocated.
If you want to learn more about what is
dynamically allocated and fixed size,
you can read from here. Basically,
dynamically allocated option will allow
your Ubuntu operating system to expand.
The disk size, if required,
and fixed size is the fixed size,
so we want to allocate the space and disk
size dynamically.
That's why we have chosen this option
here, which is dynamically allocated,
and now click on next,
and on the next window you can choose the
file location. This will be the location.
Where your Ubuntu operating system files
will be downloaded and installed on your
Windows operating system. So,
if you don't have the good reason to
change it, just leave it as default. Also,
you can choose the virtual hard disk size
from here. By default,
it's 10 GB selected here, but...
Let's say I would just want to increase
it to 100 GB,
so I'm going to just move it around 100
GB,
and then I'm going to just click on
Create. Okay,
so once you create this machine,
you will be able to see this new machine
here, which is Ubuntu 20.0.
So, just select this machine,
don't press on the start button yet;
you just need to select this Ubuntu
machine which you have created,
and then click on the settings option. So,
on the general settings,
you will see some options which we have
already.
chosen at the time of creating this
machine which is Linux and the version is
Ubuntu 64-bit.
Now click on Advanced Settings and then
in the Shared Clipboard option you just
need to choose it bidirectional and then
drag and drop also bidirectional that
will allow you to share your files.
Between your host machine,
which is Windows in my case,
and your virtual machine,
which will be Ubuntu bidirectionally,
so you will be able to copy and paste
into your Ubuntu from your Windows
operating system, and vice versa. OK,
so in the description,
you can give any description here.
And, in the disk encryption,
you just leave it as default. Now,
I'm going to just go to the system option
here, and in the motherboard option,
you can leave everything as default.
You just need to go to the processors
here, and by default...
VirtualBox will allocate 1 CPU to your
machine, so if you have the option,
you can increase it to whatever CPU you
want to use. So, for the safer side,
I always go up to this green mark here,
okay, which is for in my case.
You can increase the CPU size later, also.
Okay, in the display settings,
just leave everything as default,
and then move to the storage section here.
Here,
you need to provide the location of your
ISO file wherever you have downloaded
your Ubuntu ISO file.
So you just need to click on the empty
option here.
So just click on empty under the
controller.
So just choose the CD icon option here
and then click on Choose a disk file from
here. Okay,
so just click on Choose a disk file from
here and then you just need to browse to
the location where you have.
Downloaded your Ubuntu ISO file,
so I'm going to just copy the location
here, and then paste it here,
and then select the ISO file from here,
and then click on open. So,
once you have selected your ISO file
using this CD icon,
you will see the name of your ISO file
here. Also, let me just...
Move it further,
you can see the exact name of my ISO file
here, Ubuntu 2004 Desktop AMD 64. So,
once you have done that,
you can do other settings from here also,
but I will leave everything as default
and click on OK,
and once you have done all those settings,
you are ready to start your Ubuntu
installation.
So, here,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
select Ubuntu 20.
04 and click on the start button here.
And you can see the installation of
Ubuntu is going to start in a few seconds.
You can just close these warning signs
here,
and now you will see this kind of window
here. So, on the left hand side,
you can choose the language in which you
want to install Ubuntu.
You can see many languages are given here,
but for now I will choose English as my
language,
and then I will click on the "Install
Ubuntu" button here.
Now, in the next window,
you will see the keyboard layout. So,
from here,
you can choose the keyboard layout,
whatever keyboard layout you are using on
your laptop or on your keyboard. So,
in my case, I am using a German keyboard,
so I can just move to the German keyboard
option here. So,
I am going to just search for...
The German keyboard, which is this one,
you can choose any other keyboard from
here. OK,
so I'm going to choose the German
keyboard,
and then on the right-hand side I will
just choose German as the language here,
and then you can also test your keyboard
by typing something.
In this box,
so just choose your keyboard language
here, and then click on "Continue" button.
And here, on this window,
you will see update and other softwares,
so I normally just leave it as normal
installation option checked,
and also I leave this option also checked,
which is download updates while
installing Ubuntu. Also,
I'm going to just check this option also,
which is install third-party software for
graphics.
and Wi-Fi hardware and additional media
formats.
So just check all the options which I
have checked and then click on continue.
And here in the installation type,
just leave this option as default which
is erase disk and install Ubuntu.
So this is not going to.
Erase anything because you are installing
Ubuntu on your VirtualBox;
you are not installing Ubuntu on your
hardware, right? So don't worry,
it's not going to erase any disk or
anything from your Windows operating
system.
Just leave it as it is disk and install
Ubuntu, and then click on Install Now.
Now,
here you will see this warning which says,
if you continue,
the changes listed below will be written.
I will just click on Continue button here.
Now, in the next step,
you can choose the location which is
nearer to your physical location.
So I have chosen this location which is
nearer to my physical location and then
I'm going to click on the continue button.
And here,
you can just give the name to your Ubuntu
operating system. For example,
I'm going to just write code bind here as
the name, and as the computer name here,
I can even remove the virtual box from
the end,
because I just want to give the same name.
As the computer name also,
and also as the username,
I will just leave it as code bind.
If you want to change these names,
so let's say you want to give the
different username here,
you can do that also,
and then you can just provide the
password.
I'm going to just provide the password.
For now, it's a weak password,
but you might want to provide the
stronger password than this,
and then you just need to confirm this
password, and once you are done with that,
you just need to click on the Continue
button.
And now the installation of Ubuntu will
start on your VirtualBox.
So now at this step,
you don't need to do anything until
Ubuntu is installed on your VirtualBox.
So you just need to wait for some time
until this installation is finished.
So,
I will also wait for the installation to
be finished.
And after some time you will see this
kind of window which says,
installation is complete.
You need to restart the computer in order
to use the new installation.
So I'm going to just click on the Restart
Now button.
And at this point, it says,
please remove the installation medium,
then press enter.
So I'm going to just press enter here.
And now I can see the Ubuntu operating
system is starting.
And now I can see this login window here.
So if you remember,
this is the username which I have given
to my Ubuntu operating system.
So, I will just click on this user,
and then I will provide the password
which I have given at the time of
installation, and then press enter. So,
first of all,
you will see this kind of welcome window
here.
You can click on the skip option here,
and also you can just click on the next,
next.
And next, and then click on done,
and you will be able to see your Ubuntu
desktop here, right? So,
when you just click on this maximize
button,
now you will see that this desktop is not
maximizing,
so for that we need to install a tool
called VirtualBox.
Guest additions. So,
for installing the VirtualBox guest
additions,
what you need to do is you need to open
the terminal,
so you can just click on this option and
then search for terminal here,
and once the terminal result comes,
you just need to click on the terminal
option.
Now, once your term.
Okay, so the video is there.
I think somebody has a question.
Yes, very good.
Okay, to answer your question, yes,
if you have used another VM for big data
systems, you can use it. But see,
for this course, actually,
you will be assigned lab faculties soon,
or lab facilitators, as they called it.
So I'll be giving you pointers on what to
do.
The lab faculties will run you through
the course.
They will set up and walk you through.
through this thing and if you have any
concerns, questions,
we can discuss it during our contact
hours here.
So I'm okay with this,
but like it's better to confirm with the
lab faculty who is taking it.
Okay,
so let's quickly go over some basic
things.
See the video is uploaded on this shared
folder,
which I think I have shared with you
earlier.
So this is the link here which I have
shared, so I'll reshare it here.
So this video is present here on this
link and you can go and then check it out.
Now, what happened here? So,
you must have heard quite a lot of new
terms,
like somebody was talking about
VirtualBox being the hypervisor,
VirtualBox being the virtual machine
monitor. When somebody, I mean,
not somebody,
the video presenter had mentioned about...
virtual machines, guest machines,
multiplexing, host, and arrange. Now,
this is going to be our life going
forward.
In the sense like we cannot live without
understanding these terminologies.
So if you look to your right,
the big picture.
We are familiar with,
so far we have been working with the
physical hardware, right? Like,
what does it mean the physical hardware?
It comes to us in a box,
packaged in a box.
What does that box contain?
It contains a processor,
it contains some memory,
it contains a storage, the thing,
it contains network, it contains Wi-Fi,
it contains other, you know,
fancy utility hardware,
it contains like ports and things like
that.
No.
There is something which is called as a
hypervisor or a new technology called as
a virtual machine manager or virtual
machine monitor which sits on top of this
hardware and then it creates this guess.
Earlier when we brought any hardware or
laptop, what does it have?
It used to come with a single...
Like there used to be something which the
manufacturer sets up by default,
which we call it as BIOS.
And after that BIOS and all is configured,
then there is a OM software which is
loaded,
or an OM operating system which is loaded.
So you can get Windows, you can get Linux,
you can get Unix, not Unix,
you can get different flavors of Linux
versions.
Or, if you go for a separate Mac hardware,
you get a Mac OS kind of software,
so each one has its own quirks,
and then that is all we have been
utilizing it.
All are what do you call like adult life
since we started using computers and
studying this thing.
Now comes the concept where...
an alien entity has come up and this
thing so far in our laptop,
the operating system was the king.
In the hence,
all the critical core kernel level
activities was done by the operating
system only.
It had unrestricted access and things
like that. Now,
somebody came up with this vague idea
saying like, okay.
The hardware is so big enough that why
should only one operating system sit
there?
I can utilize the same hardware and
create multiple operating systems and
each operating system can be packaged as
a machine. That is what you saw here.
He had a Windows 10 machine.
He downloaded a Ubuntu image and then
created this scene.
Now,
one misconception to clear here is when
we say we need to create a new operating
system,
we would still require the basic
necessities of creating that software.
Like you need to have an image existing
of that particular software or OS which
you are going to give.
In this case, it was Ubuntu. Tomorrow,
if you are creating a Windows,
you need to have a license copy of the
SIG.
So there is a license cost associated
with operating system,
which you will have to bear for. Normally,
when you think of virtualization,
all these costs are included in the cloud
service providers agreement.
and then bundled to you as a this thing.
So the cost they charge you is normally
inclusive of all these, what do you call,
like OS cost.
Typically Linux and all these Ubuntu kind
of this thing, DBN or this thing,
comes free of cost unless you go for the
pay version.
Now,
that clears the role of the hypervisor.
Now, what is the...
The hypervisor is the one which will sit
alongside the OS and control the guest
listing.
Consider that as a nanny to your child.
Now, you have, let's say,
taking the child to a daycare center. Now,
the daycare center...
operates what,
there are teachers and then there are
like, you know,
nannies to take care of your kid.
What is the role of the nannies to ensure
that the child doesn't run amok and then
get into trouble? Like, for example,
some daycare centers might have
staircases because most of them run out
of houses or things like that.
So they are put there as a security
person who will ensure that like these
children, small children,
do not go outside the given bounds.
They don't go anywhere else.
They are always monitored.
They don't put their hand into the wall
sockets and get electrocuted,
or they don't loop up.
what do you know,
slip and fall in the bathroom and kind of
the scene.
So what are we trying to say here is like,
the guest OS is all a machine.
A machine needs to access privileged
content. Now what is a privileged content?
It means like it needs to access the CPU,
it needs to access storage,
it needs to access input output devices
for actions.
But in this case, they are only a guest.
So some mechanism has to be put into this
place so that the guest need not think
that like, okay, it is somewhere there,
but like it has a full access of the
physical machine.
That is the role of the hypervisor.
The hypervisor will always jump in.
And for each guest request,
it will jump up.
And whenever there is a critical access
for request for those kind of privileged
access,
like input output device memory and
things like that,
this hypervisor will jump up,
ask the guest what it wants,
translate it with the base host
communicate dialogue,
and then the host will give this,
and then it is translated.
So that is what an effective nutshell
translation or virtualization does.
Even though this was the earliest version
of virtualization,
nowadays we have come from software
virtualization to hardware virtualization
and hardware virtualization is the norm
in these days. Still,
you need to understand like what the
problem is.
with respect to virtualization was,
why this came into picture,
because the way the x86 chips in those
days, like Intel x86 chips,
like 8086 series chips were designed,
and these were the, what do you call,
like architecture of the chip design in
those days, and that is what.
cause these kind of issues.
So the key terms to remember here are
given. VMM is a virtual machine monitor.
Hypervisor or VMM is the same. Multiplex,
we'll keep hearing very frequently as we
go forward.
Multiplex means like many or several.
on a single shared point.
Host is the base physical hardware.
Guest are the VMs which are created.
What is the difference between the
physical hardware and the host? Yes,
the physical hardware and the host is the
same. There is no difference.
It is just given here just to depict that
like a.
Then,
when there are different types of
hardware setup, like, you know,
bare metal kind of setup at that time,
a single set of physical hardware can
spawn multiple clusters of hosts also,
so that time is there,
but now right now it is like you can
assume it as one-to-one on this thing.
Don't worry,
we have a separate session for x86, Rahul,
like I'll explain it in more detail
tomorrow because we cannot do justice for
that in 5 minutes. But again,
when we talk about the architecture of
x86,
what they decided is like the computer
hardware initially when they designed x86
was all...
set to go through the kernel, this thing.
And then initially when it came through,
the request could come.
There were several privileged layers,
just like you go and say like, okay,
like in a big organization,
let's say the lower grade employees will
not have access only from floors one to
five.
the top tier VP will have access to all
the floors,
and then the managing director will have
access to the top most floor kind of
thing,
and then it is he who makes these kind of
decisions, etc. So in the same way,
when they designed the x86 chip,
they had this rings of OS.
Or, like,
I know the OS rings in the x86
architecture setup,
which we will talk about in detail in the
next class,
but this is very important to understand
about utilization,
because if we don't understand the
concept between VM host guest.
and VM and guests have the same
hypervisor,
things should be a little bit difficult
moving forward.
How the rules can be set?
So I didn't understand your question,
Shekhar.
So what rules are you talking about?
The hypervisor itself is like a complete,
what do you call,
like a packaged OS and things like that.
So everything will be built into it.
So which rules are you talking about?
Okay, VM setup. That depends upon like,
there are several factors which are there
which is optimal.
Like when you saw the Oracle VirtualBox,
there are certain parameters built into
VirtualBox which first gauges the
physical hardware's capability.
So you can try it on your machine and
then if you see there,
it will be different from what you get in
there.
So it will read your physical machines,
the thing.
What does it read? It reads like, okay,
what is your current CPU available?
How much? Because remember,
when we talk about hypervisor,
one thing we all tend to forget is like,
if you just load too many guests on your
this thing,
then you're overcrowding your existing
place and then you're likely to crash
your existing machine.
So that is why that green line and things
are there.
So it reads off all those configurations.
And plus, you can also have for, you know,
the large scale commercial things,
they have configuration files which tells
us like, okay,
how much of RAMAN to allocate to each one
of them. And depending upon those things,
it will be there.
Now,
a quick introduction on the origin of
virtualization.
How many of you have seen the movie
Hidden Figures?
You already seen the movie Hidden Figures?
If not, watch it. It's a good movie.
It talks about the advent of IBM into
NASA also. I mean,
that is not the core concept of the movie.
The core concept of the movie is like the
space machine and things like that.
It's a very interesting movie.
But if you see in the early 70s and 80s,
when the hardware was being built,
Ahh.
This VMM.
If VMM doesn't block or does anything,
it just, yeah, okay, we say block it,
it apportions it for the guest VMs.
Whatever you configure out of your
hardware,
it will reserve a portion of that for
your guest VMs to work on this thing in a
way, yes.
E.
So coming back to the origin of
virtualization,
what happens here is in the early days,
I'm talking about like, you know,
70s and 80s,
when computers used to occupy an entire
room.
Like if you see the first two images,
the entire room was occupied by the
initial IBM processors.
was an expensive thing.
And then like the users were limited,
like they had to wait and then do this
thing.
Users had to run their requirements into
the coding department.
The coding department will punch it into
the computer using a punch card.
So punch card is nothing but a series of
instructions.
And while the thing is punching,
it has to be weighted.
So the initial concept of the thing
saying like, okay,
we bought it for the university,
why can't we share it across the world
with other universities also?
So if they have some computing
requirement, let them come here,
we'll charge them.
So that like the cost of buying this
thing is offset and then we do it.
So that is how this idea came in and that
was purely timeshare.
So in the initial day,
what they did is like, okay,
when somebody else is running,
the next batch will come in and then
they'll start punching it into this.
And so by the time that execution
finishes, this punch data is available.
And so they had a, what do you call,
like a suite schedules set up.
which enabled them. So moving from there,
technology has gone through a lot of,
what do you call,
like ups and downs and transformations
with advent in technology and things like
that. And if you see.
The technology which drove this was
delivered as early as like, you know,
2000, I think.
So if you see as early as 1998.
But why do you think it didn't, you know,
come up to speed in 1998?
Why weren't we studying?
We should have been masters of cloud
computing by now.
Why did cloud computing take a good
decade, 2015 or 16, to start?
The reason being,
remember the cloud computing
Genesis of Cloud Computing was because of
the development in other technologies.
One was virtualization and other assisted
technologies which came up in the early
2000s.
The other core thing which lacked was
like, you know, the network,
the advancement in network connectivity,
3G, 4G, 5G,
and all those things have come up.
which has aided or like, you know,
given a rapid boost to this thing.
So that is why it took some time for this
to happen, this thing.
Right. Hardware was like expensive.
Nowadays, like, you know,
the entire thing has turned.
Hardwares are becoming affordable,
but the cost of software is increasing.
So the breakthrough came with the time
sharing,
then time sharing led to virtualization.
Virtualization means like converting a
physical layer into software defined
entity.
And that software defined entity
masquerades as a physical entity where
nobody knows we are actually dealing with
a software defined entity.
That is why all this scale up, scale down.
pay as you go and things like that makes
more sense right now. Twenty years back,
if you go and say, like, okay,
I'm going to do this thing,
everybody will collectively laugh at you
and say, like, okay,
please give me some of the things which
you are smoking.
I'm also more interested in that.
So that is how the technology behind
these kind of things has happened.
To aid or push Cloud Computing into the
forefront technology,
as we have somebody's face.
Yeah, so many reasons like reluctance,
new technology and things like that.
Slowly people overcame and now like, okay,
everybody has gotten a fair feeling for
it and then now you are okay using this.
So in single word, what is virtualization?
Virtualization,
we can define it as a computer
architecture or a technology which allows
multiple virtual machines to be
multiplexed on the same physical hardware.
We know what is multiplexed.
We know what is virtual machines.
We know what is a physical hardware,
which is a host.
Now,
the multiple hardwares which run can be
of multiple operating systems.
So I can have Windows, I can run Linux,
I can run Mac OS,
I can run anything on the same thing.
Don't confuse it with multi-boot.
Multi-boot means you have two operating
systems separately loaded on this thing,
and then you'll have to switch between
them. You cannot run both simultaneously.
Here, you can run the base,
that is the host,
and the guest simultaneously.
And not only you,
anybody else also can come and then
access the host as if they are used.
So by doing this,
what are we trying to achieve?
We are achieving hardware efficiency.
The hardware cost is further come down,
so making computing at scale easier.
So when we say come load computing,
pay as you go, scalable elasticity,
this is the key driver for providing
those scalable architecture,
intelligent resource management,
et cetera.
Now when we talk about virtualization,
why go through all these pains?
The core thing is to maximize resource
utilization, reduce the cost,
flexibility and agility,
availability and resilience.
The thing like when you talk about
resilience means like, okay,
today if one VM fails,
I can just switch to another cluster and
then assign that VM to you quickly
without.
you even knowing something has happened.
All because everything is a file,
I can just swap it and then do it. Now,
in the image, when he said like,
when he was conferring this thing,
he said like, okay,
keep the image type as VDI,
keep the memory as this and things like
that.
Now that is the difference I told you
earlier.
Like you asked me, right,
like what is homogeneous and things like
that.
Now this is where it tends to get a
little bit tricky.
Somebody might use VDEI,
this virtual disk image,
then there is VMDKs,
then you have Hyper-V cluster difference
disk and things like that. Now,
when we do have these kind of disk images,
portability between cloud service
providers becomes a little bit things
because some of them are non-standard.
You will have difficulty porting from,
for example,
like Ken Zen Hypervisor to AWS because
you will have to 1st run it through AWS's
image check tool, which will tell you,
okay,
whether this is compatible and do the
thing. So this is why.
I told you, like,
homogeneous for a particular server is
fine,
but like when you have a multiple set up,
there is heterogeneous.
These kind of backend enabled features
will differ. The type of storage,
the memory which you use,
the file storage which you use,
and things like that. There are, it is,
of course, you might say, like, okay,
it is a disk image,
it is stored on a disk image.
But how I implement it is like this thing.
It is just like, okay,
I'm conducting this PPT,
Murli Sir is conducting this PPT,
Hari Kishan Sir is conducting this PPT.
None of our PPTs are going to be the same
because I'm more familiar with more
visual kind of content.
I don't know about the others.
They might be with a different content.
They might be practically approached,
practical, what do you call,
like approach to the class and things
like that.
But ultimately, all three of us,
the core objective is what?
To teach you about cloud computing and
things like that.
So that will be achieved.
But how we achieve it is there. Now,
what is compatible and things like that
is left to the end user to see how much
of trouble it takes to reconcile and then
rework on these things.
The multiple VMs can be run access from
the single machine. Yes, that is correct.
Okay.
Imagine cloud without virtualization.
Can you even, I mean,
that is a no-brainer question. You cannot,
if you say...
The cloud doesn't,
if I say cloud doesn't need
virtualization to run on,
but it will be highly inefficient.
Do you agree to the statement or not?
I don't need virtualization.
I can just simply host and then provide
you services. But then,
do you think like it is practical or not
is the question.
question of scalability,
rapid scalability, rapid provisioning,
everything will be thrown out of the
window because for each and every request,
you have to have something created,
physically put in,
and then made to move out of the scene.
So virtualization, as I said earlier,
is a key enabler for cloud technologies.
Without which,
we couldn't have progress to what we are
seeing.
And it gives you a lot of flexibility,
even though it brings in a lot of
additional pains and things like that.
It is a better option than compared to
this thing. Like for example,
the aggregators like S Ride, Quick Ride,
Q Ride, and things like that.
They have come in place of your local
Uber and things like that.
They are better than Uber and this thing,
but they have their own set of problems.
It's not without problems that these apps
come in and then do.
But they make our life easier because you
don't have to hassle around with the
Ubers and...
The OLAS and other, you know,
taxi providers,
and you have a more better control on
whom you choose, what to choose.
If you are a driver,
you have the option to select your
passengers whom you want to carry forward
and things like that,
so that is why I said enabler for
virtualization.
this thing, sorry,
enabler for cloud is virtualization
technologies.
But virtualization itself is not a simple
technology involved because we have this.
And on the brighter side of this thing is
like just because virtualization is
present,
today folks are able to maintain a very
lean amount of man force on cloud. We can
have everything sitting at a remote place
and monitor.
You don't need that many physical
resources to be sitting and monitoring
machines on a day in and day out basis.
So, we'll stop at here for today,
because this is going to be a bigger
topic for discussion on the X86
architecture that we will start from
tomorrow. So,
any further last questions before we
break for today?
Yeah.
Okay.
I think it's only Ravi Kiran who has just
raised his hand and then forgot to ask a
question.
Probably he's still not yet back from his.
Request session.
And somebody said like I went for masala
dosa. No,
I didn't go for masala dosa guys.
Today it was something different and you
are welcome to my house.
Okay, folks. Catch you up later.
Have a good week. Probably next week,
right?
I may not be able to join at 9 o'clock,
so is it okay if we shift the session
late in the evening?
Would you have an issue with that?
I'll talk to professors and see like we
can have it probably in the evening.
So you tell me like what is the major
consensus here?
Because I have some guests coming in and
then I have to drop them off at the
station.
So I won't be available at the morning
time. So yeah, 5pm should be fine.
Yeah, session from.
I'll do one thing, I'll just,
we'll talk here,
I'll just post some messages and then
like I'll ask the team to, you know,
sort of set it up for you. I'll just.
Saturday is Independence Day, boss.
So most of you might be taking a long
weekend break.
So I'm okay on Saturday if you have no
issues joining on Saturday.
OK, I'll float a few times, and then,
like, I'll talk a bit.
Yeah, that is also there. See,
either that or what we can do is like,
we can do it sometimes in the middle of
the week, like probably Wednesdays,
let's say 8 to 10 or something in the
mid-week,
just one-off session we can conduct.
That will also be better,
like if Saturday and Sunday are...
fact for you guys one day in the week,
like that will be great. Wednesday,
Friday or something like that,
we can do that.
Okay, so I mean, see,
we'll have to come into some consensus
because whichever way is possible,
we'll try to do that.
And then I'll let you know guys on this.
Yeah.
Thank you all.